Okay בוקר
טוב *Boker tov* today's דף daf *daf* is ע"ז *ayin zayin* בבא
בתרא *Bava Batra* 77
and we pick up in the middle of ע"ו עמוד ב *ayin
vav amud bet* about a third from the bottom and we're picking
up where it says לימא אביי Abaye ורבא *leima Abaye ve-Rava*. So
the line starts with the word רבא Rava *Rava*, it is ten
lines from the bottom and we had just gotten through a whole
very important discussion about how one transfers a שטר חוב shtar chov,
*shtar chov*, a document of debt where you're not just transferring the
physical paper but you're actually transferring the loan. So שמעון Shimon *Shimon*
owes ראובן Reuven *Reuven* a hundred dollars and now ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
wants to transfer the debt to לוי Levi, *Levi*. This is something
that gets done a lot that people sell off debt. You want
to transfer the debt to לוי Levi *Levi*. ראובן Reuven *Reuven* doesn't
know if he'll ever collect it, לוי Levi, *Levi* will pay fifty
dollars now, now שמעון Shimon *Shimon* will owe לוי Levi *Levi* the
money. So how does ראובן Reuven *Reuven* transfer the debt? Physically giving
the שטר shtar, *shtar* isn't enough, a whole discussion about אותיות osios
*otiyot* letters meaning the abstract debt being transferred. Is it enough to
do a מסירה mesirah. *mesira* of the שטר shtar *shtar* a handing
over of the שטר shtar *shtar* and contextualize and explain that it's
for the purpose of transferring the debt? Or do you also need
in addition to the מסירה mesirah *mesira* do you need a שטר
shtar. *shtar* that is written that makes it clear that the debt
is being transferred, that a שטר shtar *shtar* to transfer the שטר
shtar *shtar*? So that was the conceptual, the big question which we're
going to return to. In the middle of it we got into
this issue about רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*. In one place רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*
said that a boat can only be acquired through מסירה mesirah, *mesira*
handing over like the rope or whatever that holds down the anchor
or whatever, some type of a piece of the boat that's attached
to the boat. And in another place רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* said that
a boat is purchased by משיכה meshikha *meshikha* by drawing it. And
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* reconciles that by saying it depends whether you're
in a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, *reshut harabim* a public domain, there
מסירה mesirah *mesira* will work, משיכה meshikha. *meshikha* will not, or if
you're in a סימטא *simta* some type of an alley, and in
an alley משיכה meshikha? *meshikha* will work. There's a debate between תוספות
Tosfos *Tosafot* and the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* whether does מסירה mesirah *mesira*
also work in an alley but it's clear that in a רשות
הרבים *reshut harabim* only מסירה mesirah *mesira* works. So in a רשות
הרבים *reshut harabim* is where רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* said מסירה mesirah *mesira*
works and in a סימטא *simta* that's where רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* is...
and in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* only מסירה mesirah *mesira* not משיכה
meshicha, *meshikha*. And in a סימטא *simta* that would be where משיכה
meshichah *meshikha* would work. Okay so now the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going
to wrap that up and then turn back to the issue of
about transferring a debt. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
לימא אביי ורבא *leima Abaye ve-Rava* again ten lines from the bottom
דאמר כרבי k'Rebbi. *de-amar ke-Rebbi*. So אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* are
the ones who say that in a רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* only
מסירה mesirah *mesira* works, משיכה *meshikha* does not. And that's what רבי
Rebbi *Rebbi* said. In a רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* מסירה mesirah *mesira*
works. And the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* who argued on רבי *Rebbi* in
the ברייתא braisa *baraita* we quoted yesterday said no, you can't do
מסירה mesirah *mesira*, you have to take the boat out of רשות
הרבים *reshut harabim* and bring it, do a משיכה *meshikha* and bring
it into a סימטא *simta*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying well
does that mean that אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* are limiting themselves
to רבי *Rebbi* who's like a דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*? Because אביי
*Abaye* and רבא *Rava* are saying that in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*
only מסירה mesira *mesira* works and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* are not
allowing מסירה mesira *mesira* to work, they're insisting that you do משיכה
*meshikha*. So is that what we're talking about? So the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says is that true נמי כרבי *nami ke-Rebbi*? אמר רב אשי
amar Rav Ashi, *Amar Rav Ashi* אי דאמר ליה לך חזקי וקני
*i de-amar lei lekh chazeki u-knei* הכי נמי *hachi nami*. No, if
when you were transferring the boat the seller said go take possession
of it, take hold of the rope or whatever it is and
take possession, he was doing a מסירה mesira *mesira* and it was
clear he was intending to do a מסירה mesira *mesira*. So then
everybody would agree, רבי *Rebbi* and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* would agree
would both say מסירה mesirah *mesira* does work in רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim*. So what the גמרא gemara. *Gemara*'s saying is we can have
אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* who say מסירה mesirah *mesira* works in
רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* go both like רבי *Rebbi* and the חכמים
Chachamim. *Chachamim*. And a ספינה *sefina* could be purchased by מסירה mesirah
*mesira* in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* if it was clear
that
that is what you were trying to do. You said לך חזקי
וקני *lekh chazeki u-knei* that you used the language of מסירה mesirah
*mesira*. הכא במאי עסקינן *Hakha be-mai askinan* but in this case where
רבי *Rebbi* and the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim* debate about מסירה mesirah *mesira*
in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* or do you have to do משיכה
*meshikha* into a side street? So what's the case? דאמר ליה לך
משוך וקני *de-amar lei lekh mshokh u-knei*. The seller actually said go
do משיכה *meshikha*. And therefore that's the question. If he had said
we're going to do this through מסירה mesirah *mesira* everybody would agree
it would work. So אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* that say מסירה
mesirah, *mesira* works in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* are going like everybody.
But the scenario was he used the language of משיכה *meshikha*. מר
סבר *Mar savar* קפידא *kafida*. So the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* say well
you gotta do משיכה *meshikha*. When he said משיכה *meshikha* he was
being מקפיד makpid *makpid*, he was saying I only want you to
acquire this through משיכה *meshikha* and מסירה mesirah, *mesira* won't work and
you have to drag it into the סימטא *simta*. ומר סבר *U-mar
savar* but רבי *Rebbi* holds מראה מקום הוא לו *marei makom hu
lo*. No, you're making, you're giving him an offer, you're saying you
should feel free... free to take this home. Go bring it into
your own garage. I am done. The sale will be final. Take
possession. Go take it home. But you are not saying that it
would only be acquired in that way. And therefore according to רבי
you can do the standard קנין kinyan of מסירה. mesirah Okay now
that’s obviously a very big דוחק dochok because if the debate of
רבי and the חכמים Chachamim when whether it was מסירה or משיכה
was only in the narrow case where a person framed it in
a particular way and you had the question of whether he was
מקפיד or not, how could the whole ברייתא braisa have left out
that scenario? The ברייתא just says רבי says מסירה, the חכמים Chachamim
say משיכה. And now what we’re really saying is that they really
fundamentally have no disagreement in terms of the basic way that קנינים
kinyanim can be done for a ship and they also and they
basically both agree it can be done by מסירה in רשות הרבים,
but they have a debate if it’s phrased in a particular way
what we think the owner meant. Anyway, that’s what the גמרא’s Gemara
saying in order to get רבי and the חכמים to be in
or אביי and רבא to be in agreement with both רבי and
the חכמים. Okay so that wraps up that discussion about a boat,
is it מסירה or is it משיכה? And just to repeat what
we said the other day which is also that מסירה literally handing
over, it’s a debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether you need to
physically hand it over to do מסירה or is it enough that
you verbally hand it over by saying go take possession of it
לך חזק וקני, lech chazek vekni, which is the language that the
גמרא Gemara used, is that sufficient without the physical handing over? All
right, now we are going to get back to the major theme
which is this issue of transferring a שטר shtar חוב, transferring a
debt and how do you do that? So אמר רב פפא, amar
Rav Pappa, האי מאן דמזבין ליה שטרא לחבריה, hai man de-mazbin lei
shtara le-chavrei, somebody is selling a שטר, shtar a promissory note, a
debt to somebody else, צריך למכתב ליה tzarich lemichtav lei קני הוא
וכל שעבודא דביה. kni hu ve-chol shibuda de-bei. You have to write
in it, you take possession of the debt and all of the
liens of this debt. So again, if שמעון Shimon owes ראובן Reuven,
a hundred dollars and ראובן Reuven wants to transfer the debt to
לוי, Levi so ראובן Reuven gives לוי Levi, the original שטר shtar
that says שמעון Shimon borrowed from ראובן Reuven a hundred dollars, he’s
going to give that to לוי, Levi okay, but now לוי Levi
has a שטר shtar, that says שמעון Shimon owes money to ראובן,
Reuven what does that do? Oh, so that’s why מסירה isn’t enough
according to the חכמים, you also need a שטר. shtar, And now
ראובן Reuven is going to write a שטר shtar to לוי Levi
that’s going to say I ראובן Reuven am transferring the debt that
שמעון Shimon owes me, I’m transferring it to you לוי, Levi. and
you לוי Levi, should take possession of it and all of the
liens that I have on שמעון’s Shimon property I am transferring to
you. And now לוי Levi has in his possession the original שטר
shtar. that says שמעון Shimon owes a hundred dollars to ראובן Reuven
and the שטר shtar that he got from ראובן Reuven that ראובן
Reuven wrote to לוי Levi, that says I ראובן Reuven am transferring
this debt to you with all of the liens. Okay, so רב
פפא Rav Pappa is spelling out what that language is that has
to be written, קני הוא וכל שעבודא דאית ביה, kni hu ve-chol
shibuda de-is bei, to tell you according to the רשב"ם Rashbam two
things. Number one, to inform you what is the necessary language, and
also to implicitly tell you that he is ruling like the חכמים
against רבי that handing over the original שטר shtar is not enough,
you need this other שטר shtar? to come along with it to
make it explicit in writing that the debt is being transferred from
ראובן Reuven to לוי. Levi All
right, אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi says
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמריתי לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא, amrisi leshma'asa kamma
de-Rav Kahana, I told over this discussion to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana,
ואמינא ליה, ve-amina lei, טעמא דכתב ליה הכי, ta'ama de-chsav lei hachi,
הא לא כתב ליה הכי לא קני. ha lo chsav lei hachi
lo kani. So I said to him, you know, it sounds like
רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying that you need to write this
additional שטר, shtar מסירה isn’t enough, we’re going like the חכמים because
without an additional שטר, shtar then even though ראובן Reuven is transferring
the שטר shtar to לוי, Levi לוי Levi would not get the
debt and he would not get the liens without this additional שטר.
shtar Meaning, in other words, מסירה is not enough. It’s ruling like
the חכמים you need מסירה and a שטר shtar to transfer a
debt. So okay, that’s implicitly what רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying.
הא
לא כתב ליה הכי לא קני. ha lo chsav lei hachi lo
kani. And if he didn’t write that, then even though ראובן Reuven
is giving the שטר shtar to לוי, Levi? לוי Levi doesn’t get
the debt. So he says, how could that be? Like why else
is he giving him the שטר? shtar לצורו פי צלוחיתו הוא צריך?
le-tzoro pi tzluchosav hu tzarich? What, does לוי Levi need this שטר
shtar to serve as a bottle stopper? Meaning, isn’t the very fact
that ראובן Reuven is giving this שטר shtar. to לוי Levi itself
evidence that he is transferring the debt to לוי? Levi Why does
he need another שטר shtar to go with it? לוי Levi doesn’t
want this שטר shtar just to use as a bottle stopper. So
אמר ליה amar lei and he said back to me, אין, in,
לצור ולצור, letzor u-letzor, without an additional שטר shtar I will say
that לוי Levi only got a bottle stopper, you know, without something
making it explicit that what is being transferred is more than the
physical object, without that second שטר shtar that says that the debt
is being transferred. and the liens are being transferred then yes I'm
sorry all לוי Levi gets is that physical piece of paper but
he does not get the actual loan itself that it represents. Now
the רשבם Rashbam says you know if לוי Levi paid $50 for
this $100 debt he didn't pay $50 for a bottle stopper. So
the רשבם Rashbam says okay fine it might be clear that לוי
Levi. was expecting to get the debt but that does not mean
the debt got transferred. So if we can and therefore if ראובן
Reuven wanted to back out and says you know what I'm going
to keep the debt I'm not selling it to you he'd be
entitled to debt did not get transferred. He would have to give
לוי Levi back his 50 bucks. He doesn't get 50 bucks and
לוי Levi just gets a piece of paper okay clearly but bottom
line is if there's no שטר shtar that accompanies it the debt
did not get transferred and we are not going to say well
it's implicit he wanted the debt so that should suffice. His desire
to get the debt does not make it that that was a
sufficient act of transferring the debt. The piece of paper's not enough
you need an additional שטר shtar to make it to make it
explicit and to concretize the reality that the debt is being transferred
from ראובן Reuven, to לוי Levi. not just the piece of paper.
Okay so this is just really the explication of the two sides
of do is אותיות נקנות במסירה osios niknas b'mesira or is it
מסירה and a שטר. shtar It's obvious what people are trying to
do with the מסירה but will that desire be enough or do
you need the שטר shtar. to accompany it to really effect the
transfer of the debt itself? So now we pick up at the
top of עז עמוד א. ayin zayin amud aleph. אמר אמימר Amar
Ameimar says אמימר Ameimar הילכתא hilchasa והלכה v'halacha is אותיות נקנות במסירה
osios niknas b'mesira כרבי. We that
against what you know רב פפא Rav Papa was saying before you
can transfer a debt purely with handing over the original שטר shtar
and we rule like רבי אותיות נקנות במסירה. osios niknas b'mesira. So
you would think that okay that sort of is that and that's
clear enough but it's you see there's this huge תוספות Tosfos here
also a very big תוספות Tosfos on the previous דף and it's
not at all so clear. Why is it not at all so
clear? Because there's a question about what the גירסא girsa was. Some
have the גירסא girsa the exact opposite. They the גירסא girsa that
others have and that תוספות Tosfos prefers is הילכתא hilchasa אין אותיות
נקנות במסירה ein osios niknas b'mesira כרבנן. k'rabbanan.
The הלכה halacha is like רב פפא Rav Papa was saying handing
over the שטר shtar. is not sufficient and we rule like the
רבנן rabbanan that to transfer a debt you need to both hand
over the שטר shtar and to write a second שטר shtar, where
ראובן Reuven is saying I am transferring the debt that שמעון Shimon
owes me and the liens I have on שמעון's Shimon property I
am transferring them to לוי. Levi, Okay so even though you have
a הילכתא hilchasa two different גירסאות girsos not at all clear how
we actually conclude about how you transfer a debt. Now אמר ליה
רב פפא Amar lei Rav Papa now we're going to read the
continued גמרא Gemara like תוספות Tosfos because it just makes the continuation
reads a lot better assuming the גמרא Gemara has just ruled that
you need both to hand it over and a שטר shtar and
that handing it over is not enough. Let's take a look. אמר
ליה רב אשי לאמימר Amar lei Rav Ashi l'Ameimar said רב אשי
Rav Ashi to אמימר Ameimar גמרא וסברא. gemara u'sevara.
This idea that you just ruled again we'll take תוספות's Tosfos approach
you just ruled you need both מסירה and a שטר shtar, to
transfer a debt. Is that a גמרא Gemara a tradition that you
have or is that something that you have like just concluded that
way because that's the סברא sevara the position that makes sense? אמר
ליה Amar lei גמרא. Gemara No that's my tradition of how we
rule. אמר רב אשי Rav Ashi says רב Rav אשי סברא נמי
היא. sevara nami hu. You know what there's also a סברא sevara
why we should say this that you need both the handing over
and the written שטר. shtar Why? דאותיות מילי נינהו. D'osios mili ninhu.
In the end of the day אותיות osiyot it's funny like we're
calling the debt letters okay and now we're using another word very
similar to letters מילי נינהו mili ninhu it's just words. The debt
is an abstraction. The physical שטר shtar, as a physical thing is
just a piece of paper. You're not trying to transfer the piece
of paper you're trying to transfer the debt that it represents. So
that's מילי נינהו mili ninhu that's an abstraction. That's what you're trying
to transfer when you're handing over the שטר. shtar אותיות מילי נינהו
Osios mili ninhu ומילי במילי לא מיקנן u'mili b'mili lo miknan and
words aren't transferred with just words it's just more words. Okay
words words words words words words. So what does that mean? So
according to תוספות Tosafot. it makes a lot of sense. Here's why
מסירה isn't enough. You're trying to transfer something that's just an abstraction
you're trying to transfer the debt not just the physical piece of
paper. If ראובן Reuven gives this piece of paper this original שטר
shtar to לוי Levi and he says here I am I'm handing
this over to you and by my handing this over to you
you you. now own the debt that שמעון Shimon owed me. Okay,
so we're saying, look, the debt is an abstraction. You can't transfer
that abstraction by just saying words, right? The way in which קניינים
kinyanim are effectuated is through like the something physical that represents the
physical reality of what is happening. That's all of these קניינים, kinyanim,
משיכה, הגבהה, hagbah, you're taking physical possession. The debt is an abstraction.
How are you going to suffice to now transfer this debt by
just the words you're using to contextualize what the handing over of
the document is? That's not enough. You need something more than just
words. So now you're going to write a new שטר, shtar. and
the new שטר shtar. says, "I am transferring the money שמעון Shimon.
owes me and the debt שמעון Shimon owes me, I'm transferring it
to לוי Levi. and I'm transferring the liens," and you're handing that
over
to לוי. Levi That's already, you've now taken this abstract debt and
you've concretized it in the שטר, shtar and you've concretized the transfer
of it in the שטר shtar because now it's a physical document
that is written that is expressing the transfer of the debt to
לוי, Levi, and now לוי Levi gets and takes possession of the
physical document that expresses the idea that he has, that the money
is now owed to him. So it makes a lot of sense
that you need it to be made real through a שטר, shtar
and that therefore מסירה is not enough. You need מסירה and a
שטר shtar, to transfer a debt. So that reads very nicely according
to תוספות. Tosafot, I'm not going to try to read it according
to the רשב"ם because it's very, very difficult to think that the
גמרא Gemara says the alternative reading: מסירה should be enough because it's
only words and therefore a שטר shtar shouldn't be able to do
anything. It's a very difficult read. It is much better to read
this like תוספות, Tosafot which is מסירה is not enough because מסירה
by itself is just words and you need to concretize those words,
you know, through the writing of a שטר. shtar... Okay? And that's
why אותיות are only acquired through מסירה and a
שטר. shtar Alright. Now the גמרא says: Is that really true? That
you cannot transfer something abstract with just words? That you would actually
need a שטר shtar to concretize it in order to transfer it?
והאמר רבה בר יצחק אמר רב Veha'amar Rabba bar Yitzchak amar Rav
but didn't רבה Rabba בר bar יצחק Yitzchak say in the name
of רב and now we're going to have a whole thing that
doesn't seem relevant, but we'll see in the end the case that
is somewhat relevant. Even then it won't make so much sense, but
you have to wait till the end of the discussion
to see why we're bringing all of this in. ואמר רבה בר
יצחק אמר רב: Va'amar Rabba bar Yitzchak amar Rav: שני שטרות הן.
Shnei shtarot hen. There are two scenarios of a שטר shtar, when
you're selling a field. Okay? זכו בשדה לפלוני וכתבו לו את השטר.
Zachu basadeh leploni vekitvu lo et hashtar.
I want to gift a piece of property of mine to somebody.
So the person doesn't have to be around. זכין לאדם שלא בפניו.
Zachin leadam shelo befanav. You... I can take somebody else who can
receive and take possession of this on that person's behalf even not
in their presence. So I call over ראובן Reuven and I say,
"ראובן, here, go ahead and, I don't know, do a חזקה chazakah
on this field or we'll do a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, you
know, go ahead, you know, take a hanker- I'll take a handkerchief
from you and you shall take ownership of this field on behalf
of שמעון. Shimon זכו בשדה זה לפלוני." Zachu basadeh zeh leploni. Okay,
I'm gifting him this field. וכתבו לו את השטר. Vekitvu lo et
hashtar. Not only that, I actually bring over two people, okay? I
bring over, I don't know,
ראובן and שמעון Shimon and I say, "Take possession of this field
for לוי." Levi And then I go further and I say, "You
know what also? Write up a שטר shtar for him. Write up
for him a deed that says that I actually have gifted him
this field and he now owns this field." זכו בשדה זה לפלוני
וכתבו לו את השטר. Zachu basadeh zeh leploni vekitvu lo et hashtar.
חוזר בשטר ואינו חוזר בשדה. Chozer bashtar ve'eino chozer basadeh.
Once they do the קנין, kinyan, whatever they do, חזקה, chazakah, חליפין,
chalipin, now לוי Levi owns the field. But if they have yet
to have written the שטר, shtar.
since I made it two separate things... first I told them "take
possession of the field" and then I said "and write a שטר"...
shtar? so until that שטר... shtar since the שטר shtar. is... can
only be written because I've authorized it... until that שטר shtar. has
been written and given to לוי, Levi I can always back out.
לוי Levi owns the field as soon as they do the קנין,
kinyan, whatever the קנין kinyan is. But until לוי Levi gets the
שטר, shtar I always have the right to back out of it.
Now תוספות Tosafot has a question: If it were a sale, maybe
I wouldn't. Maybe לוי Levi could say "I'm entitled if I paid
the money to get a שטר shtar with it." But here we're
talking about a case of a gift, and I can back out
of giving him the שטר. shtar, תוספות Tosafot also asks a question:
Why does it... it obviously hurts לוי Levi if he can't prove
it. Why does it benefit me? What do I get out of
him not having a שטר? shtar, And תוספות Tosfos talks about like
it might just hurt my reputation; people know I'm selling property, they'll
think that they can take advantage of me. Anyway, I don't want
to get into all of that. Okay, but the basic point is
I can back out of the שטר shtar. until actually it's given
to לוי Levi, even though he takes possession as soon as the
קנין kinyan is done.
That's scenario number one. חוזר בשטר ואינו חוזר בשדה. chozer b'shtar v'eino
chozer b'sadeh. Now if I say to ראובן and שמעון על מנת
שתכתבו לו את השטר, al m'nas shetichtevu lo es hashtar, take possession
of this field for לוי Levi. on the condition that you will
also write for him the שטר. shtar, So now they and they
do a קנין. kinyan. So that קנין kinyan and לוי's Levi possession
of the field hinges on him eventually getting the שטר. shtar I
still retain the right to back out of the שטר shtar. until
he gets it. So in that case חוזר בין בשטר בין בשדה.
chozer bein b'shtar bein b'sadeh. I can reverse my opinion about the
שטר shtar until he gets the שטר, shtar I'm in control. And
if I do reverse my opinion about the שטר, shtar that would
also undermine the sale because I said take possession on the condition
that he gets the שטר. shtar Okay, fine. All right. Does not
seem to be too much of a חידוש, chiddush, it's clear if
I say on condition, it's on the condition. You know, the biggest
חידוש chiddush here is that I can back out of having him
write a שטר, shtar of writing a שטר shtar, in the first
place. All right. ורבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב הונא שלשה שטרות
הן. v'Rabbi Chiya bar Avin amar Rav Huna: Sheloshah shtaros hein. No,
there's actually three scenarios of gifting a field with a שטר. shtar
Okay, תרי הדאמרן, trei hadamran,
the two that you just said. אידך, idach, and the third one,
אם קדם מוכר וכתב את השטר, im kadam mocher v'kasav es hashtar,
כההיא דתנינא, k'hahih d'sanina, כותבין שטר למוכר אף על פי שאין לוקח
עמו. kosevin shtar lamocher af al pi she'ein lokeiach imo.
Let's say
I
went ahead—those are cases where the שטר shtar was not yet written
even after the transfer has been made. Let's deal with, he says
there's a third scenario where the שטר shtar. was written before the
transfer had been made. I wanted to go ahead and gift my
field to לוי Levi or sell it to לוי, Levi,
and you know, I really needed the money, and when I was
going to finally find a buyer, I didn't want to have to
go around waiting to find somebody who was going to draw up
a document. So I had a סופר sofer draw up a document
in advance of the sale. And I now have a document that
says that I sold or I gifted this field to לוי. Levi,
Now, it's still in my possession. Okay, if לוי Levi. were to
take—get this, he could claim, rightly or wrongly, that he owns the
field. But but the סופר sofer can write it to me, it's
like, you know, it's like pre-signing a check, like signing a blank
check or whatever. If I want to be stupid enough to sign
a blank check and carry it around in my wallet, that's up
to me. All right, so I have a שטר shtar, that says
I sold this field to לוי Levi or I gifted it to
לוי, Levi, and I'm carrying it around before I have even transferred
it yet to לוי, Levi but it should be on the ready
when I do transfer the field to לוי. Levi כההיא דתנינא, k'hahih
d'sanina, like we taught: כותבין שטר למוכר אף על פי שאין לוקח
עמו. kosevin shtar lamocher af al pi she'ein lokeiach imo. You can
make—write the שטר shtar for the seller even though the buyer is
not there. In that scenario, then I go ahead
and
now לוי Levi actually takes possession. Either ראובן and שמעון take possession
on behalf of לוי, Levi, לוי Levi actually does take possession, he
does a חזקה, chazakah, whatever he does. In in that scenario, once
if the שטר shtar has been pre-written, כיון שהחזיק זה בקרקע נקנה
שטר בכל מקום שהוא. keivan shehechzik zeh bakarka niknah shtar bechol makom
shehu. As soon as the act of קנין kinyan is done on
this field—חזקה, chazakah, שטר, shtar whatever is done to take possession of
the
field—then since the שטר shtar for the field, the ownership document has
already been written up, it now automatically belongs to the buyer or
to the person who received the gift. So even though it's still
in my back pocket, once we transfer the field, that person now
owns the שטר shtar as well. Okay, וזו היא ששנינו, v'zo hi
sheshaninu, and this is what we taught: נכסים שאין להם אחריות נקנין
עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות בכסף בשטר ובחזקה. nechasim she'ein lahem achrayus
niknin im nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus bechessef beshtar u'vechazakah. So there's a
קנין kinyan called אגב. agav. The קנין kinyan called אגב agav is
when you take possession of real estate, which is נכסים שיש להם
אחריות, nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus, property that has liens, meaning real estate.
You can
also—that act of taking possession can also allow you to take possession
of מטלטלין, metaltelin, of chattel, of things that are נכסים שאין להם
אחריות. nechasim she'ein lahem achrayus. Obviously the person has to be willing
to sell it to you. But if I want to basically sell
you my dining room chairs and my plot of land, you could
either do a separate הגבהה hagbahah on each one of my dining
room chairs, you know, or do משיכה or do whatever, and then
do חזקה chazakah on the plot of land. Or if I'm trying
to transfer them all to you, you can just do חזקה chazakah
on the plot of land and say with the חזקה chazakah I'm
doing on this plot of land, I also am taking possession of
your dining room chairs, and that would work. That's considered אגב. agav.
נכסים שאין להם אחריות, nechasim she'ein lahem אחריות achrayus, things that don't
have liens, meaning מטלטלין, metaltelin, chattel,
נקנין עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות niknin im nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus
are possessed together along with... So the same way that is true
about my dining room chairs, it is true automatically. In that case,
I have to say, when you're taking possession of this land, you
should also be taking possession of my dining room chairs. You don't
get to take anything of mine without my agreement. So that's an
אגב agav where I'm explicitly bundling it together. But in the case
where I have the document of sale of the land already pre-written
and in my back pocket, then even if I don't say anything,
that's considered like the automatic go-along with the land. And when you
take possession of the land, you automatically get the document that goes
with it. Okay, so he said that's a third scenario of land
and the שטר. shtar The first two scenarios are you took possession
of the land, the document wasn't written yet, the owner can back
out of writing the document. And this is the document was already
written, and as soon as you took possession of the land, you
automatically get possession of the document. Now, what does that have to
do with anything that we're talking about? Well, very little, okay, because
here's how תוספות Tosfos explains it, but תוספות Tosfos himself sort of
throws up his hands and realizes that this is not very relevant.
But it seems like what the גמרא is saying is the following,
is that ah, look, in this case, לוי Levi. took possession of
the field, he automatically got the שטר, shtar the שטר shtar is
מילי, mili, it's an abstraction, right? It's not about he got possession
of the piece of paper, he actually now owns the שטר shtar,
and that serves as evidence for him, as proof for him that
he is the rightful owner of that field. And he got that
שטר shtar without a שטר shtar accompanying it, just with taking possession
of the field. So how can you when you transfer a debt,
do you have to write another שטר shtar. to accompany it? Doesn't
that show you that מילי, mili, that words can be transferred even
without a שטר shtar accompanying it? Now, the reason that is a
very bad analogy, and תוספות says this, is because in this case
with the field, לוי Levi is getting the שטר shtar, written in
his name. The שטר shtar says I have sold or gifted this
field to לוי, לוי is the owner of it. So you don't
need another שטר, shtar. the words of the שטר shtar are themselves
relevant and written in the document and are going over to לוי.
Right, it is very different when I want to transfer a debt
and it's not represented in the שטר shtar because now somebody else
is going to be the creditor, and I can't just say my
words to frame it, I need to concretize the new relationship and
the new abstraction through something written. Here the very words themselves are
directly relevant and they're already written in the שטר. shtar So it
is not a great analogy. But somehow the גמרא thinks ah, look,
here you can transfer a שטר without another שטר, why can't you
do it in our case? Okay, and let's see what the גמרא's
answer is.
אגב שאני. Agav shani. No, there it's different. There it's not just
with מסירה, it's with אגב. agav. That you get it through doing
a קניין kinyan on קרקע karka and that's more powerful and therefore
you can transfer the שטר without another שטר. But in our case
of transferring a debt, you're not doing it by אגב, agav, you're
doing it by מסירה, you're handing over the document. And therefore, because
that's just an abstraction about the debt, you need another שטר to
accompany it. Again, this is a very non-unsatisfying גמרא because the big
difference between the cases is not one is a physical handing over
of מסירה and the other is אגב agav through possession of land.
The big difference is that in this case with the land, you're
giving לוי the שטר that is written in his name and that
says exactly what it needs to be saying. And in our case,
you're taking a debt that's owed to me and a שטר that's
written to me and now we're trying to transfer it to another
party and we need to write something else up to make it
clear what the new relationship is. Anyway, but this is the answer
the גמרא gives. Okay.
Now, how do I know that אגב agav is a powerful קניין?
אגב kinyan agav. שאני, דהמטבע דלא נקני בחליפין. dehamatbea delo nikni bechalipin.
Because when I, if I want to transfer actual cash, money, a
pile of coins, I cannot transfer that through חליפין, chalipin, like a
קניין סודר, kinyan sudar, even though a קניין סודר kinyan sudar works
on almost anything, because money is like in a different category than
objects. Money is what you use to buy objects, objects is everything
else. So it's harder to take possession halachically of money because most
of the קניינים kinyanim work on objects, not on the money that
is paid for the objects. So you cannot do חליפין chalipin to
take possession of a pile of coins. And nevertheless,
ואגב ארעא נקני, veagav ara niknei, but you can take possession of
coins through קניין kinyan? אגב. agav So אגב works. is a super
powerful קניין *kinyan* and it works even on coins which are very
hard to be קונה *koneh* and therefore it'll work to transfer a
שטר *shtar* in ways that other things won't be able to transfer
a שטר *shtar*. Okay, כי הא דרב פפא הוה ליה תריסר אלפי
זוזי בי חוזאי *ki ha d'Rav Pappa hava lei treisar alfei zuzei
bei Chuzai*, Rav Pappa had 12,000 זוז *zuz* in the, was owed
to him by this family of חוזאי *Chuzai*, and it's a little
bit of a question: was it just money that was owed to
him or was it actually the coins themselves were in their possession?
ואקנינהו ניהליה לרב שמואל בר אחא אגב אסיפא דביתי *v'akni'inhu nihaleh l'Rav
Shmuel bar Acha agav asifa d'veitei*. So Shmuel bar Acha was going
to where this family was and he wanted Shmuel bar Acha to
collect the money that was owed to him, but if he did
not transfer the ownership to Shmuel bar Acha, these people בי חוזאי
*bei Chuzai* would have refused to have given him the money. They
would say, "We're not giving you the money; we're only going to
give the money if that because you, let's say something happens when
you're bringing it back to Rav Pappa, and then Rav Pappa will
say the debt was never paid. We're only going to give up
the money if we actually will be considered to have totally in
this act of giving you the money to have paid off the
debt." So the way that would happen is that what Rav Pappa
did is he transferred the debt or transferred the ownership of the
money to this Shmuel bar Acha, so Shmuel
bar Acha was able to go to בי חוזאי *bei Chuzai* and
say, "Rav Pappa transferred the money to me, you now owe that
money to me, give it to me," and they gave it to
him. Okay.
And he transferred it to him, how did he transfer it to
him? אגב אסיפא דביתי *agav asifa d'veitei*, by the porch of his
house, by transferring ownership of a little piece of land
to Shmuel bar Acha, and through Shmuel bar Acha taking that land,
that allowed him to then now take possession of this whole big
$12,000 worth of coins that was in the house of בי חוזאי
*bei Chuzai*. All right, and then he went to בי חוזאי *bei
Chuzai* and he said, "I now owe the money, give me the
money," and they gave him the money. Okay. And then Shmuel bar
Acha brought it back to Rav Pappa and then he was going
to give it to Rav Pappa because ultimately Rav Pappa wanted his
money. This was just a way to get בי חוזאי *bei Chuzai*
to pay him. Okay. כי אתא נפיק לאפיה עד תבך *ki ata
nafik l'apei ad Tavakh*, when he came back to Rav Pappa, Rav
Pappa went out to greet him until the city of תבך *Tavakh*;
he was so thrilled that finally he had recovered this money that
was owed to him. So you see that he was able to
transfer the money through a קניין אגב *kinyan agav* even though he
would not have been able to transfer it through חליפין *chalipin*. Now
I a little bit moved back and forth between saying whether he
was transferring a pile of coins, which seems to be the case
of the גמרא *Gemara*, or whether he was transferring a debt. And
this gets into all these complicated issues about making somebody הרשאה *harshaa*,
giving somebody power of attorney, making them as if they're an owner
of the debt even though they're not technically an owner. We don't
have to get into that. But for our purposes, the point was
that אגב *agav* worked for the transfer of money where חליפין *chalipin*
would not, so אגב *agav* was more powerful, and that's why אגב
*agav* works to transfer a שטר *shtar* even though normally when you're
trying to transfer a שטר *shtar*, if it's a שטר *shtar* of
a debt, מסירה *mesira* would not be enough; you need מסירה *mesira*
and כתיבה *ksiva*, and that's why because it is abstraction, it is
מילי *mili*, it won't transfer just with words; it needs also to
be written in a document, מסירה *mesira* plus כתיבה *ksiva*. And that
is the end of our discussion of אותיות נקנות במסירה *otiot niknot
b'mesira*. As I said, there's different ways in which this, of גרסאות
*girsos* of this גמרא *Gemara*, but I read it in the way
that makes the most sense, that you need both מסירה *mesira* and
a שטר *shtar*. Okay, we'll just finish up to the משנה *Mishnah*.
אבל לא מכר לו את העבדים ולא את המרצופין ולא את האנטיקי
*aval lo machar lo et ha'avadim v'lo et hamirtzufin v'lo et ha'antiki*,
when you sell a boat, you don't sell the slaves that go
with the boat, or the pouches. Nowadays we would say the containers,
like a container ship, and the אנטיקי *antiki*. What's אנטיקי *antiki*? מאי
אנטיקי *mai antiki*? אמר רב פפא עיסקא דבגווה *amar Rav Pappa iska
d'veigava*, it's the actual commodities, it's the actual
wares that are being carried by the ship that are in the
container. That itself obviously, I mean that would seem obvious, you don't
sell the containers and you don't actually sell the wares of the
ship as well that are being stored in those containers. Okay, we
will end here for now.